<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation for reformation, published and commanded (to be obserued as law) by the high and mighty Philip the fourth, King of Spaine, for the gouernment of his kingdomes. Containing 23. seuerall chapters, wherein his Maiesty with the aduise of his councels hath ordered, and reformed many notorious abuses in the commonwealth. Faithfully translated out of the originall Spanish coppy printed by his Maiesties command</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1623 Feb. 10. English</title>
            <author>Spain. Sovereign (1621-1665 : Philip IV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22992.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S126332</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849884</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849884</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15056</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 970:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation for reformation, published and commanded (to be obserued as law) by the high and mighty Philip the fourth, King of Spaine, for the gouernment of his kingdomes. Containing 23. seuerall chapters, wherein his Maiesty with the aduise of his councels hath ordered, and reformed many notorious abuses in the commonwealth. Faithfully translated out of the originall Spanish coppy printed by his Maiesties command</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1623 Feb. 10. English</title>
                  <author>Spain. Sovereign (1621-1665 : Philip IV)</author>
                  <author>Philip IV, King of Spain, 1605-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 86, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Dawson?] for Nathaniell Butter, Nicholas Bourne, and Thomas Archer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1623]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Giuen at our court of Madrid, the tenth day of February. 1623.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf bears a coat of arms on verso; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title page has "hie and mighty".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19844 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>coat of arms of King Philip II of Spain, also used by Philip III, Philip IV and Charles II</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PROCLAMATION FOR REFORMATION, Publiſhed and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded (to be obſerued as Law) by the Hie and Mighty <hi>Philip</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> for the Gouernment of his Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Containing</hi> 23. <hi>ſeuerall Chapters, wherein his Maieſty with the aduiſe of his Councels hath Ordered, and Reformed many Notorious Abuſes in the Commonwealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of the Originall Spaniſh Coppy Printed by his Maieſties Command.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Nathaniell Butter, Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:3"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE ſeuerall Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 1.</label> For reducing Offices in Townes to a third Number.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 2.</label> That Sutors may not reſide in the Court, in any one yeere aboue thirty dayes.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 3.</label> That Commiſſioners nor Executors of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions may bee ſeut.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 4.</label> That fiats of examination of Clearkes of theſe Kingdomes, bee not allowed for the ſpace of twenty yeeres.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 5.</label> A preſcription or reformation in the exceſſe of Seruants, Houſehold-ſtuffe, and forniture of houſes, and in the apparrell of men and women.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 6.</label> That nothing made of Wood or any Mettall be garniſhed or gilt with Siluer or Gold, and that there may not be taken for the making or faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the fifteenth part of that which it ſhall weigh being of gold, and the ſixt being of ſiluer.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 7.</label> That no kind of thing may be imbrodered.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 8.</label> That there be made no Hangings for the Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of ſtrange ſtuffe, and eight yeeres are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the wearing out of thoſe that are made.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 9.</label> That neither Gold nor Siluer be worne in ſtuffe of ſilke, or trimming.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:15056:4"/>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 10.</label> That Trimming be not worne vpon garments.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 11.</label> That Cloakes of Silke be not worne.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 12.</label> That Cloth, or ſtuffe of Wooll, or Silke, made within or without the Dominions may not bee ſold without it haue a marke.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 13.</label> That nothing made out of the Kingdome may be brought in.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 14.</label> That they ſhall weare no bands, but of the twelft part of an ell, and the cuffes but of the eight breadth, both without garniſhing.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 15.</label> What Titles each Ranke ſhall haue is renued.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 16.</label> Of the moderation of the Dowry Iuels and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 17.</label> That to the Ladies of the Court there ſhall be giuen but a Million of Marauedis in Dowry, and a Petticoat.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 18.</label> That his Maieſty will not glue any Office, nor place of Iuſtice, nor of his houſe in Marriage.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 19.</label> Priuiledges which are granted to the ſtate of Matrimony.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 20.</label> The meanes whereby the Nobility is to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 21.</label> Meanes for increaſe of People.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 22.</label> That there may not bee Grammer Schooles, but in Citties and Townes where there ſhalbe a Iuſtice or Deputy.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 23.</label> For the Abolliſhing of publike ſtewes.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:4"/>
            <head>Licence and Taxation.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LAzaro de Rios Angulo,</hi> Secretary to the Kings Moſt Excellent Maieſty, executing by his commandement, the office of Secretary of the Councell Chamber, do teſtifie vpon my fidelity, that the Chapters of Reformation which his Maieſty is pleaſed to command to be obſerued for the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdome, were taxed by the Lords thereof, euery one at the price of twelue pence, which containeth twelue ſheets, and they command that they may bee ſold for this price, and not aboue: and likewiſe they command that no Printer of theſe Kingdomes may print the ſaid Chapters: and Acts, but hee that ſhall haue licence and appointment from <hi>Hernando de Valleio,</hi> Secretary of his Maieſties Chamber: and that there may bee no doubt, of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the ſaid Lords of the Councell, nor ſupplication of the ſaid <hi>Hernando de Valeio,</hi> I gaue theſe Preſents in the Towne of Madrid the <hi>14.</hi> of February, <hi>1623.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Lazaro de Rios.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15056:5"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>coat of arms of King Philip II of Spain, also used by Philip III, Philip IV and Charles II</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>HILIP,</hi> By the Grace of <hi>GOD,</hi> King of Caſtile, Leon, Arragon, of both the Sicilies, Jeruſalem, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15056:6"/>Navarra, Granada, Toledo, Valencia, Galicia, the Malorcas, Sivill, Sardinia, Cordova, Corcyca, Murcia, Iaen, the Algarves, Algecira, Gibral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, the Canarie Jlands, the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, and of the Ilands, and firme Land of the Ocean Sea: Archduke of Auſtria, Duke of Burgundie, Brabant, and Milan, Earle of Auſpurgh, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Tiroll, and Barcelona, Lord of Biſcaye, and Molina, &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To the Infantes Our deare and welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Brethren, and to the Prelates, Dukes, Marquiſes, Earles, Priors of Orders, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, and Deputie-Lieutenants, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Caſtles, Forts, and Chaſes, and to thoſe of Our Councell, Preſidents, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Our Requeſts, Iuſtices, Marſhalles of Our houſe, Court, and Chancery; and to all Iudges, Iuſtices, Aſſiſtants, Governors, High-Sherifes, and Vnder-Sherifes, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes, Provoſts, and to Councels, Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, Mayors, Aldermen, Recorders,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15056:6"/>Town-clarkes, Knights, Squires, Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Officers, and other good men, and Subiects whatſoeuer, of what eſtate, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, or dignitie, ſoever they are, or may be, within all the Citties, Villages, Townes, and Provinces, of theſe Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and Dominions, as well, to thoſe that are, as to them that ſhall be, and to all and every one of you, to whom this Our Edict, or any thing therein contained, ſhall or may appertaine, in any manner what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>KNow yee, that Our Royall will and pleaſure is, that in theſe Our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (having acknowledged it a moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant and ſufficient meanes, for the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and conſervation of them,) there be inſtituted, appointed, and eſtabliſhed, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Bankes and Treaſuries, where may be brought in, and received, the Subſidies, and ayde moneys, which ſeeme to accord, and are agreeing, with the Lawes, Ordinances, Statutes, and Priviledges, and that there be ordained, certaine Squadrons of Sea-Forces, for the defence of the Sea, and too
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15056:7"/>the intent that by their execution, the ends may be ſecured, which are pretended for the vniverſall benefit of Our Crowne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of Commerce, and profit, and eaſe of perſons, of every condition and qualitie; it hath ſeemed neceſſary to reſtore, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to a convenient eſtate, ſome things of the government, wherein by the change of time, and other accidents, many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences haue beene found: and it may be feared, that (if they are not prevented,) may increaſe, for that the one helping the other, the effects which they procure, may be greater, and more certaine. And having by Our ſpeciall Commandement diligently diſcuſſed, and vpon the whole with great care and conſideration conſulted, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated, it was concluded, that Wee ſhould command, and by this Our Edict Wee doe command, which Wee will haue obſerved as a Law, and Act of Parliament, (as if it had beene made and enacted in Court of Parliament,) that from hence forward, theſe things following be obſerved and kept.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15056:7"/>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> Reducing of Offices to a third part.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Wee ordaine, and command, that the Offices of Maiors, and Aldermen Sheriffes, Conſtables, Bayliffes, Clarkes, Proctors of the Cities, Villages, and Towns, where (through the exceſſiue number of them) they are found inconvenient, and preiudiciall to the government, cauſing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grievances, which haue beene and are daily ſuffered, diverting the ends wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they were ordained; be reduced to a third part, in the forme, by the meanes, and with the qualities, which are contained in the Commiſſion, which for their executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Wee haue cauſed to be ſealed by Our Royall hand the day of the date hereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> That Suters may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in the Court in any one yeare, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue thirtie dayes.</head>
               <p>LIkewiſe, Becauſe by the long and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall reſidence, and great concourſe of Suters in this Court, there ariſeth preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to their houſes, and families, by the forſaking and neceſſity wherein they leaue them; and to their owne profeſſions, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they cannot exerciſe them, nor employ the time, with that decencie, and profit, as beſeemeth; and to the Offices, Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other occupations, when they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15056:8"/>them, becauſe they haue leſſe abilitie and diſpoſition, then is requiſite; for the better exerciſe, and more ſecure adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iuſtice, and for other conſiderations of equall importance, other grivances haue beene acknowledged. Wee ordaine and command, that what perſon ſoever, that pretendeth Eccleſiaſticall office, or Secular Commiſſion, Temporall charge, or place, may come and proſecute his Sute in this Our Court, and preſent the reaſons and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles thereof, for the ſpace of thirtie dayes in every yeare, and no more, and ſhall be bound to record the time of their entrance, and departure, before the Secretary of the Councell, where the Sute ſhall depend. And likewiſe the Suters, which haue now Sutes depending in this Our Court, ought to be Regiſtred within fifteene dayes, and to depart within thirtie following, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the forme preſcribed: and not bringing a Certificate from the Regiſter of his entrance, may not haue audience, not be heard by any officer, nor haue counſell, or adviſe.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15056:8"/>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> That Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, nor exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion may be ſent.</head>
               <p>ANd becauſe that by the ſending of Commiſſioners, and executors of Commiſſions, grievous inconveniences haue beene obſerved, not onely in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and adminiſtration of Iuſtice, but in the quietneſſe, comfort, and eſtate of our Subiects, (ſeeing that where they ought to haue proceeded with equitie, and Iuſtice, that the effects which from thence are wont to ariſe, to the ſervice of God, and Vs, and the good of this Common-wealth might follow,) they haue in that manner tranſcended their duties, that vſing the ſame hand of Iuſtice to their owne commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and private reſpects, they convert it to their particular profit, to the irrepacable preiudice of government, with ſuch vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, troubles, and coſts of the parties, who come to be grieved and oppreſſed, by thoſe which ſhould ſuccour and relieue them, and to be without neceſſary remedie, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that through the remoteneſſe of places of Iuſtice, which ſhould adminiſter the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife, they cannot come to demand it, and other dare not, and ſo they remaine with the grievance which they haue ſuffered,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15056:9"/>and the Commiſſioners and executors of Commiſſions, without puniſhment, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by there hath beene, and is perceived a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Iuſtice in the body of the kingdome, and in the Subiects irreparable loſſes, which daily increaſe; and therefore it is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to provide for the remedie, which the importancie of the matter requireth, and hauing conſidered, the cauſes of this miſchiefe, and that by ſpringing from cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and through the difficultie to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the particular caſes, whereby to afflict the puniſhment vpon the offenders, how much ſoever we are truely informed of the certaintie in generall, it will be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to apply the remedie, and therefore convenient and neceſſary, to come vnto the roote: Wee ordaine and command, that no Councell, place of Iudgement, Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Audience, Corporation, Vniverſitie, nor particular perſon, of any ſtate, condition, or qualitie whatſoever, for any title, cauſe, or reaſon, doe or may ſend into any part of theſe Our Dominions, any Commiſſioner, or executor of Commiſſion, nor any other perſon whatſoever, with Iuriſdiction, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15056:9"/>or inſtruction, neither in other forme, at the coſt of the parties, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, vnder penaltie, that the perſons of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, ſhall be ſeverely puniſhed; and thoſe that ſhall admit the ſaid Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſhall be perpetually deprived of their offices, which they beare, and make a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſtitution of the Fees received: and that all the buſineſſes and cauſes, wherin it may be neceſſary, to grant a Commiſſion to a particular perſon, as well of proofes, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, recoveries, executions, notificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, citations, as of other neceſſities, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, wherein hitherto they haue beene ſent, may be henceforward remitted to the ordinary Iuſtices of the Cittie, Village, or Towne, where they ought to be done. And if by any reaſon or cauſe, any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be admitted, that they be remitted to the next royall Iudge belonging to Our Court; and Wee doe onely permit, that in Our Councell, there be Iudges, diligently to enquire, and looke into the caſes, and to allow them, if warrantable by the law, but not any other, of what qualitie ſoever, and Wee command them, to procure to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15056:10"/>excuſe theſe caſes, as much as they may.</p>
               <p>AND likewiſe wee command, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is contained in this Act, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably kept and obſerved in Our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Our Revenues, and Our Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, vnleſſe it ſhall be in ſome excuſable caſe, wherein a receipt cannot be entred by the ordinary Iuſtices of Our Royall Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, as are the Impoſts, or any other member of Our Revenue, the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, conſiſteth in different pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without any ſettled being or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for in thoſe caſes a Commiſſion ſhall be graunted, having firſt of all, conſulted with the ſaid Councell of Our Revenues, and Eſchequer; and the perſon which ſhall be ſent, ſhall be ſuch as the Preſident ſhall appoint, and not in any other caſe, becauſe the adminiſtrations of Impoſts, and other Rents, are to be committed to the ſaid Iuſtices. And likewiſe, Wee doe command, that when in Our ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Our Revenues, there ſhall be made any determination, contract, or letting to Farme, there may not be allowed any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15056:10"/>Iudge, or Commiſſioner, for the execution or accompliſhment thereof, or to capitulate with the parties, but that the one and the other be done, by the ordinary Iuſtices, and their officers.</p>
               <p>ANd becauſe as well in Our Councell, as in the reſt of Our Tribunalles, Courts of Iudgements, and in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, and other Audiences, there are ſome Councellors, and Officers, which haue particular Commiſſions, whereby they name Iudges, Commiſſioners, executors of Commiſſions, and others, within and Without the Court, for the diſpatches of buſineſſes which are preſented; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſubdelegate their Commiſſions, to other particular Iudges, that out of them, they may make others, and thereby the ſubdelegated may name Officers, and ſervants. Wee ordaine, and command, that from hence-forth, all perſons of what eſtate, or condition ſoever they be, as well of Our Councell, as of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tribunalles, or any other particular perſon, which ſhall haue Commiſſion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15056:11"/>Adminiſtration, or Superintendencie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be annexed to his office, may not name, or ſend Iudges Commiſſioners, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of Commiſſions, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to diſpatch any buſineſſe, nor ſubdele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate any particular perſon out of this court, but to commit them to the ordinary Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kingdome, and to vſe their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, in the caſes and buſineſſe, which ſhall be offered concerning the ſaid Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vſing likewiſe Our next Royall Iudge, when the ordinarie Iuſtice ſhall allow of any lawfull exception, which being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to right, may make it ſuſpitious, who may not take other officers for the execution of the Commiſſion, but thoſe of the ordinary Iuſtice of that part, where the buſineſſe ought to be done, without grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wages then their ordinary Fees.</p>
               <p>ANd alſo Wee doe command, that the Commiſſion of the Kingdome, and the receiver thereof, and the receiver generall of the Fines, and Amercement of the Starre chamber, and the reſt of the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles, Chanceries, Audiences, Citties,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15056:11"/>Townes, and Villages of the Kingdome; Treaſurers, Collectors, or the particular places by the diviſions, which haue or ſhall be made, may not henceforward ſend, Iudges, or executors of Commiſſions, for the recovery of any thing, but that the ſaid recoveries be remitted to the ordinary Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
               <p>ANd becauſe there haue beene found the ſame iniuries, both in the vniverſall and particular of this Kingdome, by the Iudges, and executors of Commiſsions, which are ſent by vertue of contracts made betweene parties, for the execution of them. Wee ordaine, and command, that from henceforth the ſaid Iudges and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, may not be ſent. But it is Our will and pleaſure, that all thoſe who by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular contract made before the publication of this Statute, haue cautelated the recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of their debts, by deſtinating, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and agreeing to ſend a Commiſsioner at the charge of the debtor, may doe it by vertue of the ſaid contracts, and writings, becauſe they may not be defrauded of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15056:12"/>ſecuritie, and condition, in confidence whereof, they delivered their goods, and without the which peradventure they had not delivered them; and becauſe in ſome contracts and writings, the parties haue not beene contented to capitulate, that they may ſend a Commiſſioner, but alſo another perſon with him, and both at the charge of the debtor, (the which in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, is not neceſſary for the Recoverie, and onely cauſeth expenſes, and oftentimes an impoſsibilitie in the Debtor to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the principall,) whereby is occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his vndoing. Wee ordaine, that the Creditour, in whoſe favour the ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, with the ſaid qualities are made, may onely ſend a Commiſſioner or Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, ſo that one onely be ſent, and that he haue onely one Fee.</p>
               <p>ANd becauſe for the iuſtification of the titles of ſome Offices, and of the Fees, and preheminences, which by vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appertaine to the owners and proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, there are certaine Iudges, called Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of preſervation of Titles: Wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15056:12"/>that from hence-forth, the ſaid Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be not ſo called, or ſtyled, and Wee doe diſanull and pronounce, ſuch appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be voyde, and of none effect, and eſtimation; And Wee doe command, that thoſe that haue them, forbeare to vſe them, vnder the penaltie of two hundred Ducats, to be diſpoſed in three parts, whereof the firſt to Our Exchequer; the next to the Iudge; and the third to the Informer, and that the parties repaire to the ordinary Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, for the maintenance of the Title of the ſaid Office, and the preheminences, and rights, that by reaſon thereof belong vnto them.</p>
               <p>ANd becauſe ioyntly by providing the remedie of the miſchiefes mentioned, wee muſt cautelate and nicely looke vnto the matters; and that by committing them to the ordinary Iuſtices, they may not faile to haue the ſecurity, and effects which are fitting, as well in the ſubſtance, as in the time and manner how great ſoever the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in favour of the Iuſtices, aſwell in reſpect of the equalitie of their perſons,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15056:13"/>as of their office and place, and therefore ſeeing they are credited being of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique government, and ſo important in the Common-wealth, any other diligence or employment may be committed to their truſt, with aſſurance that they will more carefully diſcharge them, then other Commiſsioners, notwithſtanding, that herein no occaſion of danger may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine; VVee ordaine, and command, that if the ſaid ordinary Iuſtices, ſhall not wholy performe the buſineſſes and cauſes which ſhall be committed vnto them, with the punctualitie and care as ſhall be appointed, and ſet downe, by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and contracts which they ſhall haue to execute, then a Commiſſary to be ſent at the charge of the partie, which may doe and execute it, in the time, and with the Fees, as the qualitie of the matter ſhall require, and as ſhall be appointed by the Councell, Tribunall, or perſon, to whom they ſhall remit the ſaid cauſe.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15056:13"/>
               <p>BVt it is not Our will or deſire to make alterations in the proofes of Gentrie, nor in the perſons or Officers which are ſent to the qualifying of Nobilitie or Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, by the Councell of the Orders; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe herein VVee will that the auncient Lawes and Ordinances be obſerved, and the ſtile and vſe where-withall it is practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. IIII.</hi> That Fiats of Examination of Clearkes of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes be not allowed for the ſpace of twentie yeares.</head>
               <p>IN like manner by reaſon of the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which haue redounded to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, by the facilitie of admitting and allowing the Titles of Clarkes of theſe Kingdomes, and the exceſſiue number, wherevnto haue amounted the Offices, with little conveniencie of government, and with preiudice to the adminiſtration of Iuſtice, and eaſe of Our Subiects, Wee did ordaine, and command, at the requeſt of the Kingdome in the laſt Parliament, that for the ſpace of ſixe yeares, a Fiat of Clearke might not be allowed to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of any condition whatſoever, or for any title or cauſe, as more at large is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Act, which Wee commanded to be publiſhed, wherevnto VVe refer Vs,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15056:14"/>becauſe the exceſſiue number of Clearkes, and the preiudices which thence ariſe, is daily more and more diſcovered, and that by the ſuſpenſion for the ſaid time of ſixe yeares, the ſufficient remedy cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided. VVee doe command, that the ſaid terme of ſixe yeares, wherein as aforeſaid, a Fiat of a Clearke of theſe Kingdomes ought not to be graunted, nor any perſon examined for the title of it, be and be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be the terme of twentie yeares in the whole, that within the ſaid time, none may be allowed, and the contents of the ſaid Law obſerved.</p>
               <p>ANd for to prevent the fraudes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, which are committed in Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations by the Clearkes of the writing offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Number and Realities. Wee command the acts in this caſe provided by Our Councell be obſerved. In like manner becauſe it greatly importeth to the good government and adminiſtration of Iuſtice, and prevention of the exceſſes, which are found ſo preiudiciall to Our Subiects, Wee ordaine, and command, that the Clearks of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15056:14"/>Criminall Pleas, Common Pleas, of Aſſiſes, and Number of the Provinces and Reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in taking of Fees, and ſetting them downe, for the actions and writts, which they ſhall make, obſerue and keepe, that which is ordained by the Statutes, and Lawes in this caſe provided, and that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by themſelues, nor by any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon interpoſed, they receiue any more, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thing, vnder the puniſhments therein contained, and the loſſe of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and if they be not the proprietors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then of foure yeares baniſhment, and that for teſtimony and witneſſe herein, three ſingle teſtimonies may be ſufficient, as in caſe of bribery, and they may be the ſame perſons, and if they will be Informers, they may be admitted, and haue the third part of the Fine.</p>
               <p>ANd to the intent that with greater pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualitie and Iuſtice they may take the Fees, which are due vnto them, and no more, Wee ordaine, and command, that in this Our Court, and in the Citties of <hi>Valladolid, Granada, Sivill,</hi> and <hi>Cornna,</hi> none may be received or taken, vnleſſe they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15056:15"/>be firſt taxed, and aſſiſted, by the generall Aſſiſter, and that the manner of proofe, and the penalties be the ſame. And that the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Our Houſe and Court, Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Audiences, and ordinary Iuſtices of the ſaid Citties, doe not decree, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine any Sute, wherein this hath not beene accompliſhed. And becauſe the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe may be greater towardes thoſe that are priſoners, for that they little eſteeme who defend them, and are careleſſe of their liberties, VVee ſtrictly command, that in their cauſes it be executed with greater care and preciſeneſſe, and becauſe in what kinde ſoever of their Sutes they may be freed, it is vnderſtood they are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted with exceſſiue Fees, which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act of them, VVee ordaine, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that the Asſiſtor with one Iuſtice, (doing it by weeks) may aſſeſe every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Fees due by the Priſoners, which they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to be freed, &amp; which ſhall be due, and delivering them to the Aſſiſtor, the parties which ought to haue them, may receiue them at his hands; and receiving them in any other manner; We
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15056:15"/>declare them to incurre the like penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>THat in this Our Kingdome the ſaid Clearkes, and thoſe which reſide in the Offices of Provinces and Number, doe, nor may take of either of the parties, any Fees in the Sutes that are to be executed, neither for the Bookes, which ſhall be drawne, nor the proofes which ſhall be made, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the tenne dayes of the proceedings, nor for following the Sute, vntill the cauſe be adiudged; and then the Aſſiſtor having aſſiſted them, the ſumme wherevnto they ſhall amount be put into a Bill or Writte of payment, which ſhall be allowed, that the principall, and the tenth part be recovered together, vnder the penaltie, of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their offices, and diſabled to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute any others.</p>
               <p>ANd becauſe many miſchiefes doe ariſe, in that the Clearkes deliver the Writts of execution to the Bailiffes, that they ſhall make choiſe of, not onely by being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed in the ſucceſſe, whereby it is to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15056:16"/>feared, that in the Records, and other Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, they may helpe the execution, but likewiſe, becauſe thereby many Bayliffes apply not themſelues to the matter of cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall cauſes, and delicts, but ſtand waiting in the houſes of the ſaid Clearkes, that the ſaid writs of execution may fall vnto them, VVee ordaine, and command, that in this Our Court, and in the ſaid Citties of <hi>Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid, Granada, Sivill,</hi> and <hi>Cornna,</hi> every day may be brought in the writs of execution, which ſhall happen, by the authoritie of the perſon that We ſhall depute thervnto, and thoſe be by him devided amongſt the the Bayliffes by courſe, that hereby every one with equitie may participate of the fruit of their Offices, &amp; the inconveniences mentioned, as much as poſſiblie, prevented.</p>
               <p>ANd that no Bayliffe may enter in this courſe, vnleſſe he ſhall firſt bring a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony from the Clearkes of the Peace, and the Iaylor of the impriſonments, and crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſes, which he ſhall haue done for thirtie dayes paſt.</p>
               <p>IN like manner, that no Clearke in this Our Court, doe, or may take money, or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15056:16"/>any other thing, for making reports of the Sutes, which ſhall be heard before them, and the Iudges, in the firſt commencing of the Sute, or in appealing to Our Councell, Chanceries, and Audiences, and other Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunalls whatſoever, but onely thoſe, which by the Statute ſhall be due vnto them, for the entrie of the Sutes, vnder the penaltie of the loſſe of the office, if it be their owne, and if not, the baniſhment for foure yeares, and that the partie which ſhall giue it, doe looſe the right of his Sute, and that for the whole, the teſtimony of three ſingle wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes be allowed ſufficient in the forme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p>ANd becauſe We haue vnderſtood, that the publique Scriveners, and Clearkes of this Our Court, and other places of Our Kingdome, doe apply themſelues to ſeeke moneys, that the Councels, Vniverſities, and particular perſons may take them to interreſt, receiving of them betweene three or foure in the hundred, by the title &amp; name of Broakage, Wee ordaine, and command, that from hence forward they may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue money, nor any other thing, neither
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15056:17"/>this title or other, by themſelues or other perſons, nor more then the Fees, which by the Statute ſhall be due vnto them, for the writings that they ſhall make. And becauſe there followeth an inconvenience by the exceſſiue number of Clearkes, which are in the Offices, Wee ordaine, and command, that in the Offices of the criminall Pleas of Our Chamber, and in thoſe of the Province or Comitie of <hi>Madrid,</hi> there may not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the number of ſix principall Clearks, which may reſide in every Office for the executing of buſineſſe, and thoſe the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and proprietors of the Office to name at their perill, that if they be Fined, and ſhall not haue goods to diſcharge the Fine, it may be recovered of them: and that thoſe of the ſaid Chamber be approved by the Chamber of our Iudges, and thoſe of the Province of <hi>Madrid,</hi> by the Iudges, before whom the Clearkes which are proprietors of the Office, make the diſpatches of their buſineſſe, and thoſe of the Aſſiſes, or any one of them, and the proprietour which ſhall haue more then the ſaid ſixe Clearkes, We condemne in the loſſe of his Office.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15056:17"/>
               <p>And becauſe many Conſtables by diuers wayes and repreſenting cauſes and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments leſſe certaine, haue taken out ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations in ſome things concerning their offices, as are watches and wards and going out of this Court to make impriſonments, and other things; which being ſo; that they might be of more profit in the generall, by hauing more knowledge and experience in thoſe buſineſſes, and that this priuiledge and inequalitie is preiudiciall to the reſt, We command that thoſe that haue the ſaid pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of reſeruall doe deliuer them to the Preſident of our Councell within foure daies, and may not vſe them, but that they ought and doe in the whole and euery part conforme themſelues, as they are bound by their offices, without any exception, vnder the penaltie of the loſſe of their ſaid offices, and baniſhment for foure yeeres.</p>
               <p>That beſides the ordinarie Viſitor of the offices, which is named euery yeare by Our Councell, there may be named another, from three yeares to three yeares, by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident thereof, that they may viſit all the ſaid Clarks and Officers, and certifie the abuſes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15056:18"/>which ſhall be executed in the execution of their offices, commiſſions, &amp; other imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which they ſhall haue, eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the contents of this Act, allowing him thereunto a neceſſarie commiſſion, which he ſhall vſe before a ſufficient Scriue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, remouing it (if he will) out of the Court.</p>
               <p>Againe, We ordaine and command, that the Clarks of our Councell-chamber, of the Chanceries, and Audiences, may not take nor recouer the fees which ſhall be due vnto them for the Scedule, according to the lawes, vnleſſe they be firſt aſſeſt by the Aſſeſſor ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and ſetting downe vpon their fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or of their principall officers, that which they recoues and take in euery ſute, and the like is to be vnderſtood of the Relators in al the ſutes and Reſidencies, and that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the hill, they exact not vpon the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor receiue any thing, vnder the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the loſſe of their offices, and for teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie and proofe, ſingly witneſſes ſhall be ſufficient.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the exceſſe ofſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold-ſtuffe, &amp; furniture of houſes, and in the apparell of men and women.</head>
               <p>ALſo becauſe from the abuſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in attendance, houſhold-ſtuffe, and furniture of houſes, and in the apparell
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15056:18"/>of men and women, there haue proceeded many inconueniences, as well in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment and good diſpoſition, wherein it ought to be, as in the cuſtomes and eſtates, ſeeing that being voluntary expences once brought in, they are become ſo preciſe, that it is one of the greateſt burdens, wherewith the Subiects are oppreſt, and likewiſe preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to commerce and trade, albeit that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Lawes were inſtituted, which ſeemed conuenient for the preſent eſtate, when they were ordained: but it is manifeſt by time and occaſions, that they haue not procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo ſufficient, as was expected, and that wickedneſſe by contrauention, hath found out many deuices with encreaſe of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, deſiring to prouide a ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, and hauing commanded, to ſee what in this kind hath beene enacted, and to adde what ſhall be thought conuenient. We doe ordaine, and command, that no perſon of any eſtate, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, or qualitie ſoeuer, may keepe or entertaine, of Gentlemen, Pages, and Laqueyes, aboue the number of eight or ten perſons, and who ſhall execute the principall offices of the houſe, as Steward,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15056:19"/>Gentleman of the Horſe, and others; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may keepe them employed in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, to the end to accompany them or their wiues, by the title of Followers or Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſeruants, or other; ſeeing it only ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for oſtentation, and certaine inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, which are therein conſidered; and there is likewiſe imburſed, the coſt and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences which they cauſe in the houſes, and it is more expedient, that they employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues inſome other courſe of life, which may be more profitable to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the effects of a matter ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant may be ſecured, for the which the example of the King, and his Officers will be conuenient, ſeeing by themſelues alone and by their offices, they haue ſufficient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, without that the great or ſmall number of attendance can encreaſe or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh it: let them know, that We ſhall be very well pleaſed, that they continue as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, a moderation in their retinue, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that, if it may be poſſible, it be greater from hence-forward, ſo that the Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors and Officers, may not haue nor enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15056:19"/>in all kinde of attendance aboue eight perſons, that by Our example and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the number of offices and ſeruants, which We haue commanded to be done in our Royall Houſe, and by that which they ſhall doe, reducing themſelues to the ſaid forme, there may bee a reformation in all the reſt, and may proportion themſelues to their eſtate and neceſſitie, wherein they are, ſeeing the luſtre and authoritie of their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and perſons ſhall be better preſerued and kept, liuing out of neceſſitie, and plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accommodated, than by conſuming in an expence ſo ſuperfluous. And becauſe the ſeruants of the ſaid qualitie, which now they haue in greater number than the ſaid eight or ten, may haue departure and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and not vnaccommodated and idle; We command that whatſoeuer is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained concerning this Act, may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued after the expiration of a whole yeere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the promulgation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> That nothing made of wood or any met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, begarni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed or gilt with Siluer or Gold; and that there may not bee taken for the making or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, but the fifteenth part of that which it ſhal weigh, being of gold, and the ſixt, being of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</head>
               <p>ANd becauſe by garniſhing things of wood or other things, &amp; by gilding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there followeth loſſe, both in the expence &amp; making, being a thing vnprofitable and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15056:20"/>We ordaine, and command, to obſerue with all rigour, the contents in the fift Act with thoſe following, from the twentie fourth title of the compilation, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that not any other mettall may be gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, although it be plaine and ſmooth plate, vnder the penaltie of the loſſe of the peece which ſhall be ſo gilded. But Wee doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that it ſhall be lawfull to gilde all that ſhall be for Diuine vſe, and the Armes, and furniture for horſes, ſo that they be not for the vſe of the Coach. And likewiſe Wee command, that no faſhion of Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which ſhall be wrought, ſhall exceed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gold, the fifteenth part of the value of what it ſhall weigh, and being of Siluer, the ſixt part; vnder penaltie of the loſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> That no kind of thing may bee imbrode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</head>
               <p>IN like manner as concerning Hangings, let that be inuiolably obſerued, which was publiſhed by the proclamation in the yeere of our Lord, 1611, adding thereunto, that it ſhall not be lawfull to make any kinde of Imbrodery of gold, ſiluer, ſilke, or thread, neither in hangings, beds, chaires, ſtooles, canopies, pillowes, carpets, caskanets, nor
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15056:20"/>any other thing, vpon cloth of gold or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, cloth, leather, canuas, nor any other kinde of ſtuffe whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Alſo that no Imbroderer may imbroder any kinde of the aforeſaid things, nor any other, vnleſſe it ſhall be for diuine vſe, and horſe furniture, except foot-cloathes, for We will not that they be imbrodered, as neither liueries for the ſport of the Cane, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at Tilt, both on horſebacke and foot, running at the Quintaine, Ring, or other fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiuall ſports, that the diſpoſition of this law may facilitate the vſe of riding, and the exerciſe of theſe ſolemnities, and for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing and delight of the people, and may take away the obſtacle and difficulty, which is often found by the not hauing of the pompe and exceſſiue expence, wherewith they are now celebrated. We command that the contents of this branch or chapter be obſerued from the firſt day of March of this preſent yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> That there may not be made Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings for the Sommer of ſtrange ſtuffs, and eight yeares are allowed for the wearing out of thoſe that are made.</head>
               <p>LIkewiſe alſo We forbid, that no manner of perſon, of what eſtate, condition, or qualitie ſoeuer, may haue or vſe any han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15056:21"/>for the ſommer, of any ſort or kinde, though they be plaine, being wrought out of theſe kingdoms; but We permit that they may haue Damasks, ſhorne Veluets, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit cloth of gold or ſiluer, and taffeties, ſo that that be wrought within our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And for the wearing out and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Hangings which they haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodered, and of ſtuffs made out of this Kingdome, and of other things imbrode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the vſe whereof is prohibited in this Statute, We doe giue and allow thereunto the ſpace of eight yeares, which being expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, We condemne all thoſe that ſhall vſe them, and diſobey the contents hereof, in the forfeiture and confiſcation of them, and in fiftie thouſand Maravedis to be diuided in three parts, viz. our Chamber, the Iudge, and the Informer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> That gold nor ſiluer be worne in ſtuff of ſilke or trimming.</head>
               <p>IN like manner concerning faſhions and apparell, We prohibite, and altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to men and women without any diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the vſe of gold and ſiluer, in ſtuffe and trimming, within and without the houſe, in all and all kindes of garments or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15056:21"/>apparell, though they be doublets, gownes, night-gownes, caſſocks, ſhort coats and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though they be for trauell, excepting (as before) for religious vſe, furniture for the warre and horſe, in the forme as they are permitted in the Statute enacted in the yeere of our Lord, one thouſand ſix hundred and eleuen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> That trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings be not worne vpon garments.</head>
               <p>ANd alſo We do altogether prohibite all kind of dreſſing &amp; trimming, be it ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle or double, though it be of one lace alone, in al kind of garments, either of men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that they may not be worne neither in doublet, ſhort-coat, gowne, night-gowne, caſſocke, hoſe, or other whatſoeuer; neither vpon daggers or garters, for Wee permit them only to be worne plaine, of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the garment ſhall be.</p>
               <p>In like manner Wee command, that it ſhall not be lawfull to worke, neither for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Merchant or other perſon to buy (for to ſell againe) any kinde of garniſhing, or lace, trimming of gold, ſiluer or ſilke, from the day of the proclaiming of this ſtatute hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, vnder the penaltie both to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15056:22"/>and buyer, of the loſſe of ſuch trimming and lace, and of three hundred thouſand Maravedis to be applied in three parts, viz. Our Chamber, the Iudge, and Informer: and becauſe through the toleration hitherto, Wee conſider that the Merchants haue bought certain garniſhings and trimmings of gold, ſiluer and ſilke; and likewiſe the women haue bought many garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, made with them: We doe allow the ſpace of three yeeres to the ſaid Merchants for to ſell and diſpoſe of them; and to the women the ſpace of foure yeeres, to weare out their garments, and to vſe the ſaid trimmings vpon thoſe which they haue alreadie made. And as concerning men, that they may weare out thoſe that they ſhall haue made with trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: Wee allow them the ſpace of two yeeres, but that it ſhall not bee lawfull for them within the ſaid tearme, to make or cauſe to be made, any new garment with trimming, becauſe herein We will that from this preſent this Statute be obſerued. And for the more certaine execution thereof, and to preuent all deceit, We will that the trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings and garniſhings, which the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15056:22"/>now haue in their hands, ſhall be produced, manifeſted and regiſtred, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the view of them, thoſe only which they now haue may be ſold: ſeeing for this intention, and that they may be ſold, it is permitted to the women to vſe them for the ſaid time, but not to buy others for to ſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> That cloakes of Silke may not be worne.</head>
               <p>LIkewiſe We doe prohibite, that the men may not weare ſhort cloaks, long cloaks, ſhort coats nor mantles of ſilke, but only of cloth or Raſh: But Wee permit that they may weare certaine ſtuffes, as Telilias, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, Mingled ſtuffe, and other the like ſtuffes, ſo that they bee not mingled with ſilke, and that they be wrought within Our Dominions; and We permit that in winter they may line them outwardly with Silke, ſo that they be wrought within Our Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> That cloth nor ſtuffe of wooll or ſilke made within or without the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, may not be ſold with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it haue a marke.</head>
               <p>IN like manner, becauſe in the making of cloth and ſtuffe, as well of wooll as of ſilke, or mixtures of both, hath beene and is daily found much deceit, becauſe, hauing no reſtraint, they are fraudulently and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15056:23"/>made, and thereby are of little ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and durance, to the great preiudice of thoſe that weare them: Wee ordaine and command, that from hence forward it ſhall not be lawfull to ſell or buy in thoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; neither for apparell, nor for any other thing, any kinde of cloth, or ſilke, or wooll, or of both, made or wrought within or without them, which ſhall not be made and wrought conformable to the laws and ordinances of the Dominions, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine and concerne the makers and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers thereof; neither ſhall be lawfull to make any other manner whatſoeuer, vnder penaltie of the loſſe of the ſaid cloth or ſtuffe, and of a hundred thouſand Marave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis to be applied in three parts, viz. Our Chamber, the Iudge, and the Informer. And We doe declare, that the Merchants ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the penaltie of this Law, if they ſhall haue in their ſhops the ſaid clothes and ſtuffes, without the qualities that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, and for to ſell, and diſpoſe of them, which they haue at this preſent without theſe qualities, VVe allow them the ſpace of three yeares, regiſtring them in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15056:23"/>the forme aforeſaid. But becauſe in ſome part of theſe Kingdomes, there are made and wrought ſome kindes of cloth and ſtuffe, of wooll, and ſilke, which if they be well wrought, will be profitable, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient not to hinder it; VVe command that thoſe of our Councell cauſe them to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for perſons skilfull in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, and finding them to be profitable, to ſet downe and appoint an order, forme, and direction, whereby hence forward they be made, and no otherwiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> That nothing made out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may be brought in.</head>
               <p>IN like manner, becauſe by the bringing in of many commodities made out of theſe Kingdoms, as hangings, beds, chaires, ſtooles, pillowes, bed-tikes, carpets, and others, and likewiſe apparell for men and women, and others of cotton, linnen, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, alchymie, tinne, lead, ſtone, haire, and other kinds, which (being furniture for the houſe, and of vnprofitable vſage) doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the eſtate and wealth, and hinder the labour and making of thoſe, which ſhall be profitably wrought, there ariſeth great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience to the Common-wealth; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15056:24"/>that hereby is taken away from the Tradeſmen, the occupation and diſpoſition of gaining their liuing, and ſuſtaining themſelues, an infinite number remaining idle, and vnimployed, and in the dangers vvhereunto the force of the neceſſitie obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them: VVe ordaine and command, that from the day of the promulgation hereof forward, it ſhall not he lawfull to ſet or put to make out of the Kingdome, any thing made of wooll, or ſilke, or of both, (ſo that it be not Tapeſtrie of Flaunders) neither of cotton, linnen, leather, alchymie, lead, ſtone, ſhell, Iuorie, horne, haire, but that the materials and the ſimples may only be brought in vnwrought, being of the things permitted, to the end that they may bee wrought in Our ſaid kingdomes, vnder pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie of the loſſe of the thing which ſhall be ſo brought in, ſold, or bought, being made out of the Kingdome, and of thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Maravedis to him that ſhall cauſe them to be made, ſold, or bought, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in three parts, viz. our Chamber, the Iudge, and Informer: and to the intent that he may ſell and diſpoſe the things of this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15056:24"/>qualitie, which he ſhall haue at the time of the promulgation of this Edict, wee doe allow them the ſpace of two yeares, which being expired they ought not to ſell them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> That they ſhal weare no hands but of the twelfth part of an ell and the curld but eight breadth, both without gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſning.</head>
               <p>ITEM, We command, that all and euery perſon of what eſtate, qualitie, or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they be, ought and ſhall weare plaine fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling bands, and without any inuention, bone-lace, cut-worke, ſhagge fringe, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other kinde of ſetting forth, or ſtarched with gumme, powdred blew, or any other colour, or ſet with a ſteele-ſticke, howbeit We permit that they haue ſtarch; and in caſe ſome man may weare a ruffe, We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that it be only of the bredth of the twelfth part of an ell; and that the curled lettuce ruffe be but of eight bredthes, and that without any kinde of dreſſing, of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, garniſhing of ſtarch, powders, or any other thing, and that it be all in one ſingle length, not opened with a mould, or any other inſtrument, and the cuffes to the ſame ſhall be but of three bredths, and halfe a twelfth part aforeſaid, and with the like
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15056:25"/>qualities. Alſo the lettuce ruffes and cuffes of women may be vſed as heretofore, but ſo that they haue no bone-lace or other garniſhing more than one ſhagg fringe, nor may they haue any of theſe things in their falling bands, calles, falles, or any other habit or ornament, nor may they be done with powdered blew, vpon paine of loſing that which they weare contrary to this law, and of fiftie thouſand Maravedis to be diuided into three parts: viz. to the Chamber, the Iudge, and the Informer: which We command to be obſerued and executed in this Court from the firſt of March of this yeare; and in all other parts and places of this Kingdome within two moneths after the publication of this Law: And We forbid, that any man or woman open any ruffe either of man or woman, vpon paine of publike ſhame and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from this Court, or the place where they ſhall goe againſt this Law.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:15056:25"/>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> What Titles each ranke ſhall haue is renued.</head>
               <p>ITEM, Whereas on the ſecond of Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the yeare, One thouſand, ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and eleuen, We commanded to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and then was publiſht concerning the vſe of entertainment of curteſies, a Law of this tenor following: <hi>Don Philip</hi> &amp;c. Know yee, that We hauing beene informed, that there hath beene and is much diſorder, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cceſſe, and inequalitie in the entertainments, titles, and courteſies, as well in writing as in ſpeech, which are vſed among the Grandes, Gentlemen, and other perſons of theſe Our kingdomes, whereupon many inconueniences haue followed, We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thoſe of Our Councell that they ſhould looke into it, and treat of ſome forme which might be kept, that ſo theſe might be excuſed and hauing diuers times thus done, and conſulted with Vs, Wee haue now agreed to prouide and order as followeth.</p>
               <p>And though it were not neceſſarie in that which concernes my Selfe, and other Royall Perſonages to innouate in any thing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15056:26"/>which hath beene heretofore accuſtomed, notwithſtanding that others with greater obligation and care may keepe and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh that which is to be ſaid concerning this, We will and command, that in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Vs no other title be ſet in the top of the letter or paper, than <hi>Sir;</hi> nor any thing ſaid in the concluſion, more than, <hi>God preſerue the perſon of your Catholike Maieſtie,</hi> and without addition of any other curteſie or complement, the perſon who ſhall write any ſuch letter or paper, ſhall firme it: and in the ſuperſcription no more may be put, but only, <hi>To our Lord the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame order alſo is to be held and kept with the Princes the heires and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of theſe our Kingdomes, only chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that of, <hi>Your Maieſtie,</hi> into, <hi>your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and that of, <hi>King</hi> into <hi>Prince;</hi> and in the concluſion and end of the letter ſhall be put, <hi>God keepe your Highneſse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the ſame order and ſtile be kept and held with the Queenes of theſe Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which is to be giuen to the Queenes, and ſo to the Princeſſes as to the Princes.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15056:26"/>
               <p>That the Kings children male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, be only ſtiled, <hi>Their Highneſſe:</hi> in the top of the letter, <hi>Sir,</hi> or <hi>Lady;</hi> and in the end, <hi>God keepe your Highneſſe,</hi> without any other complement; and in the ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only, <hi>To my Lord N. the Kings ſonne, To my Lady N. the Kings daughter;</hi> and when it ſhall be ſaid or written abſolutely, <hi>His Highneſſe,</hi> this ſhall not be attributed but only to the Prince the heire and ſucceſſor of theſe our Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>That the ſame complement be done to the Sonnes and Brothers in law of the Kings of theſe our Kingdomes, as to their wines, and to the daughters and ſiſters in law of the ſaid Kings as to their husbands. As for that which is to be done by the ſaid Royall Perſonages to others, it is not Our will to innouate any thing of that which hath hitherto beene and is accuſtomed.</p>
               <p>In like manner We will and command, that the ſame ſtile which is vſed and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the petitions which are giuen in Our Councell, and in other Councels, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries and Tribunals, and that which is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15056:27"/>accuſtomed in ſpeech when they are in Councell, be obſerued as hitherto in all things which ſhall not be contrary to this Our letter and prouiſion, excepting only, that in the top may be put, <hi>Powerfull Lord,</hi> and no more.</p>
               <p>That in the references of all Our let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſcedules, and prouiſions where Our Secretaries were wont to put, <hi>By his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> they put, <hi>By the King our Lord,</hi> as now it is done; and that the ſame be done alſo in the references of the Notaries of Our Chamber.</p>
               <p>And that in all other ſeats of Iudgement as well belonging to the King, as any other whatſoeuer, whether the ſpeech be in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular or in publike, the petitions, demands, and complaints ſhall begin in the line, and with the ſame buſineſſe which is to be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of without placing any title, word, or ſigne of any complement either at the top or any other part, only at the end it may be ſaid, <hi>Wherefore I implore the office of your Lordſhip or Worſhip;</hi> according as the Perſons or Iudges are to whom a man
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15056:27"/>ſpeakes; and the Notaries may only ſay, <hi>By the command of N. Iudge,</hi> ſetting downe his name and ſurname only, and the name of the office of ſuch a perſon or Iudge, and the dignitie or degree of learning which he hath, and no other title.</p>
               <p>We forbid and defend, that no perſon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in word or writing, giue to any other of what eſtate or condition ſoeuer, what degree or office ſoeuer hee hath, great and preheminent though it be, the ſtile of <hi>Moſt Illustrious Lordſhip,</hi> except it be to Cardinals; for it is not Our will that they be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in this our Law. Alſo by reaſon of the authoritie and greatneſſe of the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> Wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, hee being Primate of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that all men be bound to ſtile him <hi>Moſt Illuſtrious Lordſhip,</hi> although he be no Cardinall. And We command, for Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, and Grandes, and ſuch as We command to be couered, that all men be obliged to giue them the <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> as well in writing, as in ſpeech: And alſo for the preſident of our Councell, VVe permit that hee may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, his <hi>Moſt Illustrious Lordſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15056:28"/>
               <p>VVe command alſo, that ſuch Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours as haue place in our Chappell, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely to be called and written, <hi>Lordſhip.</hi> And We permit that the reſt of the Embaſſadors which come from without theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, may be ſtile <hi>Lordſhip;</hi> but not them which goe from them to other parts.</p>
               <p>Wee permit that Marqueſes, Earles, the great Commendadors of the Orders of <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiago, Calatraua,</hi> and <hi>Alcantara,</hi> the great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendador of <hi>Monteſſa,</hi> the Keepers of the Keyes of the ſaid Orders of <hi>Calatraua</hi> and <hi>Alcantara,</hi> may be called and written <hi>Your Lordſhips:</hi> and the Daughters of Grades, <hi>Your Ladiſhips;</hi> the Preſidents of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels and Chanceries, the Priors and Baylies of the Order of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Priors of the Covents of <hi>Veles</hi> and <hi>Leon</hi> of the Order of Saint <hi>Iago</hi> during the time of their Offices, and the Vice-Royes, and Generals of Our Armies, Gallyes, and Armada of the Ocean, and he which is or ſhall be Maſter Generall of the Campe of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and thoſe which are chiefe Cities of Kingdomes, and thoſe other which haue Voice in Courts, and the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels of Metropolitan Churches, where it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15056:28"/>hath beene accuſtomed, ſhall be ſo ſtiled. And VVe will, and it is Our fauour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that ſuch perſons as ſhall giue the ſtile of <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> to the Daughters in law of ſuch Lords of Title, which ſhall be maried to the Heires and Succeſſours in their Houſes, and to the eldeſt Daughters, who of force are to ſucceed, for not being able now to haue a Brother which ſhould be preferred before them in the ſucceſſion of the ſaid Houſes, ſhall not incurre the penalties of this Edict hereafter mentioned, nor any other. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding, as Wee doe forbid that no other perſon of whatſoeuer qualitie, ſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he be, haue the ſtile of <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in writing or ſpeech, or that of <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> except he be Grande. And VVe declare that the treatie which is to be had with the wiues of Grandes, of Knights, and of other perſons, to whom (as it hath beene ſaid) it is due, and who may be called either <hi>Lord</hi> or <hi>Sir,</hi> and among themſelues by writing or ſpeech, it ſhall bee the ſame which is to bee performed to their husbands.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, We command, in that which concernes one mans writing to another,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15056:29"/>that generally without any exception this forme be held and kept, viz. the letter or paper which ſhall be written, ſhall preſtently begin with the reaſon or buſineſſe in hand, without ſetting either vnder the croſſe at the top, or in the beginning of the line, any title, cipher, or letter, and the concluſion of the letter ſhall be, ſaying, <hi>God keepe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> or <hi>your Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>God keepe you,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the date of the place and time, and vnder that the firme, without any comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment either before or after, only he which hath a title, may put it in the firme with the place from whence he hath that title. And for ſuperſcriptions, to a Prelate ſhall be put the Eccleſiaſticall dignitie which he hath; to a Duke, Marqueſſe, or Earle, that of his eſtate; to Knights, Gentlemen, and other men, their name, ſurname, the dignitie, or office, charge, or degree of learning which they haue.</p>
               <p>Nor ſhall any exception be taken or made againſt this order and forme of writing by any perſon, neither by the ſubiect writing to his Lord, nor by the ſeruant writing to his Maſter, onely
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15056:29"/>Parents writing to their children, or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their Parents may before the proper name adde that which is naturall; alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the husband and the wife may be expreſt the eſtate of Matrimonie, if they will, and betweene brothers, cozen ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, Vncles and Nephewes, that of their kinred.</p>
               <p>And We will, and it is Our pleaſure, that that which is thus ordered and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this Our letter and prouiſion be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of all men, not only within theſe Our Kingdoms, but alſo in writing to ſuch as are abſent abroad.</p>
               <p>And for the better keeping, accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and executing of all that hath beene formerly related, Wee ordaine and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that ſuch as ſhall come or goe againſt that which is here ſet downe and contained in theſe Our letters and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or any portion or part thereof, that euery one of them ſhall for the firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence pay two hundred Ducats, for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, foure hundred, for the third, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Ducats, and a yeeres baniſhment fiue leagues from this Court, and from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15056:30"/>Villages, and places of theſe Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and iuriſdiction where the ſaid law and edict ſhall be broken, the which pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niarie penalties aforeſaid ſhall be diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this manner, viz. one third part to the Informer, another third part to the Iudge which giues ſentence, and the other third part to pious vſes. In like manner ſhall fall into the ſame foreſaid penalties ſuch perſons who from hence forward ſhall vnder-hand diſſemble or giue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that their children, ſeruants, ſubiects, or any other perſons, doe goe beyond ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in word or writing to them the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie and order contained in this ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, and the tranſgreſſor or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, which haue not wherewith to pay the ſaid pecuniarie penaltie, it is Our will that for the firſt offence they be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned twenty dayes, and if it be in Our Court, that they be baniſhed and depart from it fiue leagues for a whole yeere, and if it be in any other place of theſe Our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the baniſhment ſhall be from that place and out of that country and iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for the ſecond offence the foreſaid
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15056:30"/>puniſhment ſhall be doubled; and for the third offence, they ſhall be baniſhed for fiue yeeres in the forme aforeſaid, reſeruing vnto Our Selues, according to Our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, beſides the foreſaid puniſhments, the making of ſome greater demonſtration to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſaid tranſgreſſors.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe, the obſeruation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of all the aforeſaid, being ſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and important, We command you all and euery one of you, according as hath beene ſaid, that you take notice of this Our letter and prouiſion, and that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it, the which We will haue to hold the force of a Law, Edict, and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, made and publiſht in Court; and that you obſerue, accompliſh and execute the ſame, as ſuch in and throughout euery part of it, according and as is contained therein; and that you at no time, nor in any manner wayes goe or paſſe againſt the tenor and forme hereof, vpon paine of the ſaid puniſhments, and thoſe other where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into they fall who paſſe againſt and breake the commandements of their Kings and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15056:31"/>naturall Lords, whatſoeuer lawes or edicts to the contrary notwithſtanding; All which We by theſe preſents doe abrogate, and take away, and giue for none at all, and of no value or effect: And ſo in like manner We command all Iudges and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whatſoeuer in theſe our Kingdomes, and all perſons to whom the execution and performance of the foreſaid doth or any manner of way may belong, that inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with all rigour they keepe, accompliſh, and execute it vpon the tranſgreſſors, and that, not hauing an Informer, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt them <hi>Ex officio,</hi> and hauing an Informer, that the Iudge or Iudges either not proſecuting the cauſes or giuing ouer to proſecute them, ſhall incurre and fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame puniſhments wherein the ſaid tranſgreſſors ſhould haue been condemned and executed, and into two yeeres ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from their offices: And whatſoeuer ſhall be contrary to this Our law, diſpoſed by any other whoſoeuer in theſe Our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, We abrogate and nullifie all, and command that this only which is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15056:31"/>herein, be kept, fulfilled, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
               <p>And becauſe it is thus ordained and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and that it may come to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of all, and no man pretend ignorance, We command that this Our Letter and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion be publikely proclaimed in this Our Court, and that that which is therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained be obſerued and accomplished, and executed preciſely and inuiolably in this Our Court from the time of the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in other parts and places of theſe Our Kingdomes, within thirtie daies after the publication; and that you both the one and the other, by no manner of meanes doe otherwiſe hereafter, vpon paine of the ſaid puniſhments. Dated in <hi>Madrid,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And after, on the fourth of Aprill of the ſame yeere, wherein there are two Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>That to Princes, Dukes, Marqueſes and Earles, which be ſtrangers, may be giuen the ſtile of <hi>Lordſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo We permit, that our Embaſſadours which doe and ſhall reſide in Our Embaſſies
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15056:32"/>about the Perſons of other Princes, may haue the ſtile of <hi>Lordſhip.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> Of the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Dowry, Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell.</head>
               <p>ANd becauſe the exceſſe and head, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the charges are come which are made in mariages, and the obligations which therein are introduced, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered to bee a charge and burthen to the ſubiects, becauſe they conſume their commodities, and morgage their houſes, which doth increaſe the depopulation of this Realme, ſeeing that the ſame are ſo great, preciſely the dowries muſt be ſo, whereby they are hindered. For men nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dare not nor cannot enter (by reaſon of ſo great charges) into the ſtate of Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, conſidering that they are not able to ſuſtaine them with the goods they haue, nor women haue not ſufficient dowries to ſupply them, and from thence there ariſe other inconueniences in the cuſtomes, and againſt the tranquillitie of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; We doe ordaine and command, that for ſo much as concerneth the dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, there be held, accompliſhed, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15056:32"/>that which is ordained by the firſt law of the ſecond title of the fift booke of the Recollection, and that according to the ſame, euery perſon of what eſtate, qualitie, dignitie, or preheminence ſoeuer hee be, that ſhall haue two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Maravedis, and ſo vpwards to fiue hundred thouſand Maravedis of Rents, may giue in dowrie to euery one of his daughters lawfully begotten, a million of Maravedis, and no more; and he that ſhall haue leſſe rents than the ſaid two hundred thouſand Maravedis, may not giue, nor ſhall giue in dowrie aboue ſix hundred thouſand Maravedis, and no more; and hee that ſhall ſurpaſſe the foreſaid fiue hundred thouſand Marave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, vntill a Million, and one hauing foure hundred thouſand Maravedis in rents, may giue a million and a halfe of Mara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedis in dowrie: and hee that hath a million and a halfe of rents, and ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, may giue in dowrie to euery one of his lawfull daughters, one yeeres rent, and no more, wherewith he may not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15056:33"/>twelue Millions of Maravedis, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his ſaid yeerely rent be more than twelue Millions. And likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the exceſſe in Iewels, apparell, and other things, which are giuen and made at the time of eſpouſement: Let there be kept the ſaid firſt law of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond title, of the fift booke of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection, and in conformitie thereof, that no perſon whatſoeuer, of what eſtate, qualitie, or condition ſoeuer he be, may giue, nor is to giue to his ſpouſe and wife in Iewels and apparell, nor in any other thing whatſoeuer, more than the eighth part of her dowry ſhall amount vnto which he is to haue with her, which is to be in the quantitie and forme afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. And from henceforth we make void and of no value and effect, the contracts, agreements, or promiſes which ſhall be made in any other manner, and for loſt the quantities or thing wherein they ſhall exceed in any of the aforeſaid Caſes, and We doe apply them for the ſame fact to Our Chamber.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15056:33"/>
               <p>And becauſe there may with more pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuality be accompliſhed that which is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the Ioyntures may not exceed the tenth part of that which the free goods ſhall amount vnto; We doe ordaine &amp; command, that in Our Councell chamber there bee not giuen any power for the diſpenſation therof, and from henceforth We make void, and of no value and effect, whatſoeuer power ſhall be giuen to the contrary: and for the more certainty of the execution of the premiſſes, the Notary before whom they ſhall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the writings, ſhall be obliged to giue an accompt of ſuch Contracts to the Iuſtice of the Country or place where the ſame ſhall be made; and the Notary of the aſſembly of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place, ſhall keepe a booke wherein hee ſhall take the reaſon of the ſaid Contracts, and the quantity, dowry, and Iointures: and the Iuſtice ſhal certify whether the ſaid dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and Iointures, Iewels and apparell which they haue giuen, doe exceed the quantity which by this Act is commanded; and hee ſhall execute the penalty &amp; application made for Our chamber: And that hence forwards this ſhall be put for an Article of reſidence,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15056:34"/>and this law may not be renounced, but tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XVII.</hi> That to the Ladies of the Court there ſhall be giuen but a million of <hi>marauedis</hi> in dowry, and a petticoat.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> To the end that (in Our Royall houſe things may bee ſet in good order) and Our example to be the ſureſt law, and an executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on to others; We do ordaine and command, that to no Lady of the Court there may bee giuen for her dowrie and mariage, or to ſettle her for any other way, more then the ſumme of one million of <hi>Marauedís,</hi> and a petticoat, without any other preeminence or honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble title, nor office, nor other kind of dignity, which is the very ſame that was giuen in the time of King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, my Lord and Grandfather: and with the Portugall Ladies let there be done that which was done in the time of the Kings of Portugall, before that Kingdome was incorporated with this Crowne, and that vnto thoſe of the Chamber, there bee giuen no more but fiue thouſand <hi>marauedis,</hi> which haue beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XVIII.</hi> That his Maieſty will not giue any office, nor place of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, nor of his houſe, in mariage.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> It is Our will, and We haue reſolued, that there ſhall not be giuen, nor Wee will
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15056:34"/>giue to any perſon whatſoeuer, neither for dowrie, nor preferment, nor other particular title, any place nor office of Iuſtice, nor pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke authority, nor any of our Royall houſe and Wee command that no perſon whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſo bold as to require it, neither by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nor word of mouth, vnder penaltie of Our diſpleaſure and puniſhment as ſhall bee found fitting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XIX.</hi> Priuiledges which are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the ſtate of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> To the end that for all there may bee a helpe for encreaſe, being a thing ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, and for the felicity and frequency of the ſtate of Matrimony, which thereof fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; We doe ordaine and command, that foure yeares after the day of any bodies ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, he ſhall be free of all charges and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke offices, recoueries, hoſts, ſouldiers and others; and the two firſt years of theſe foure, of all royall taxations and offices, and of the forraine money, if it happen to fall vpon them: and if any marry before the age of eighteene yeares, hee may adminiſter and enter in the eighteenth on his goods; and thoſe of his wife, although ſhee be younger, without asking any leaue of Authoritie.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15056:35"/>And to thoſe which are full fiue and twenty yeares, and are not married, may bee put to the ſayd charges and publike offices, and are bound to ſerue them, although they are in the power and houſe of their fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> That he which ſhall haue ſixe male children aliue, ſhall be free for all his life time from the ſaid charges, and publike offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And although there be any of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren wanting, the priuiledge continueth.</p>
               <p>And becauſe beſides the reaſons aforeſaid of the exceſſe in the dowries and charges, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty and want is, that many women are without meanes to bee marryed, willing to giue them ſome ſuccour; Wee doe ordaine and command, that from henceforth the goods which ſhall be <hi>(moſtrencos)</hi> in euery place, ſhall ſerue and be applied for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of poore women and orphans; and from henceforth We giue the ſame to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied for the ſame effect, notwithſtanding any lawes and orders made to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and that the ſame come into the power of the perſon which the Councell, Iuſtice and gouernment ſhall nominate, to the end that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15056:35"/>from thence it may be employed in the caſes which ſhall happen by the interuention of the ſaid Councell, hauing a regard to the age, quality, and pouertie, and other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for to qualifie pouerty, or for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of them, if in caſe there bee more then one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> That amongſt the reſt of the forced Legacies of the Teſtaments, there ſhall hereafter be put a legacy for the marying of poore women and orphans, and they ſhall be bound to leaue ſome quantity or ſumme for that effect. And Wee doe charge the Prelates to gather the ſame, and to put the ſame in good keeping, and employ the ſayd legacies, &amp; alſo the execution, as if Our moſt holy Father had beene pleaſed to grant it (as we haue deſired him,) and for themſelues in that which they can, examining the pious workes which ſhall be in their Biſhoprickes, applying them which ſhall bee found leaſt profitable, for the marying of orphans and poore ones, ſeeing it is ſo meritorious a work; and alſo the pious works which haue no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular application, in ſuch manner to put it
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15056:36"/>to this, and that of the ſmall almes which they giue, they may apply that part which they can to this worke, ſeeing in the regular there is none, which can bee ſo much for the ſeruice of GOD, and good of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and for the ſuccour and helpe of the poore.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, Wee require and charge all Prelates, of Churches, Cathedrals, &amp; Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries capable of goods in common, as well of Friars as of Nunnes, that they will iointly procure, and euery one by himſelfe, to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and helpe poore women and orphans in the places where they ſhall be, ſeeing that amongſt the obligations and almes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the Eccleſiaſticall goods and rents are bound, in the eſtate which this day this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath, this is one of the moſt precious and meritorious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> Becauſe it is very needfull, that the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which may be expected of that, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in this Law, may not bee badly put forth for want of diſpoſing and exucution, Wee ordaine and command thoſe of our
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15056:36"/>Councell, that with particular care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration they attend that all that which is afore-ſaid be kept, accompliſhed, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, alwayes procuring to vnderſtand if it bee ſo done, and in effect to prouide all that which ſhall be needfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XX.</hi> The meane whereby the Nobilitie is to be appeaſed</head>
               <p>AND becauſe hatred, malice, and other reſpects, and particular accidents haue taken ſo much place, in the meane of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing of the nobility and pureneſſe, in the Acts which are required, with ſo little credit and conſolation to the Nation, with ſo much vnquietneſſe and diſcord in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, with ſo great coſt of goods and liues, and perill in the conſciences, which is iudged in the gouernment to be the worthieſt thing to be repayred, as well for the remedying of ſo great inconueniences, &amp; by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there ariſeth generally ſo much dammage in the Kingdome and particular houſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there ſhould be maintained in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue quality and inſtitution, the holy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the profitable and laudable ends of the common benefit, whereunto the ſame tended; and which by their good
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15056:37"/>vſe, men haue beene experimented, and in ſubſtance being ſo needfull, and not to preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the ſame by the accidents in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Wee ordaine and command, that from henceforth no perſon, of what ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoeuer he bee, may not giue, nor let him giue, nor alſo to admit, nor let him admit memorials without ſubſcription, and that if the ſame ſhall be admitted in any Councell, Tribunall, Church, Colledge, or other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalty, where there is neceſſary the qualification of the nobility and pureneſſe, let no credit bee giuen thereunto, nor take place, if the ſame be generall, and render no particular reaſon of the things the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, although they cite and chooſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and although they alledge publique fame, and may onely be in order admitted for to enquire, and for no other effect, when they ſhall elect and chooſe <hi>Sanbenito</hi> or peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and the yeare wherein it was giuen, with expreſſion of the perſon whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth of the Church, or the party where he is, of the parentage which hee hath with the plaintiff, or with other <hi>individuos</hi> ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, which truly induce the minde that it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15056:37"/>is no malice; And alſo they may admit the ſame, when they ſhall manifeſt writings with equall qualities to the ſayings; or in caſe of citing of witneſſes, the ſame ſhall bee giuen before the Informer or Deputy, for in ſuch caſe they may examine the witneſſes, which therein are cited, as the Informer might exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them by himſelfe: and ſo ſhall giue no credit, as being cited in the memoriall, but for ſo much as ſhall be ſaid being examined.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the words which haue beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in difference, or extrajudicially in <hi>corril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> or in conuerſations, doe not withſtand, nor ſhall not be an hinderance to the acts of Nobilitie and pureneſſe, whereſoeuer the ſame are divulged and diſperſed, and being come to the notice of many, that the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall depoſe thereupon, as not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more notice of the qualitie of the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe, then to haue heard the ſame, nor if hee had not cauſe nor reaſon to ſpeake the ſame, ſhall not be an hinderance to the pretention of Nobleneſſe and pureneſſe, as if it had not proceeded, nor ſhall not be grounded in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other beginning, but if there be verification made thereof by the Informers, they ſhall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15056:38"/>finde that there was a ground to declare it, becauſe the perſon was noted, or by other reaſons of writings, <hi>Sanbenito,</hi> penitences, It is Our will, that they worke as the Lawe ſhall permit, becauſe in ſuch a caſe the words ſhall not worke by them-ſelues, but the cauſe and ground which there is againſt the Plaintiſſe, although the ſame are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> Becauſe all matters haue their limits and termes to make them certaine, to the end the ſame may hereafter bee held for ſuch as being paſſed in an adjudged matter, it is conſidered, that thoſe of this quality ſhould not holde the ſame, but rather a perpetuall diſpoſition: and that after many poſitiue acts of Nobleneſſe and pureneſſe obtayned and iuſtly by the ordinary and iuridicall meanes, the ſame ſhall not be executed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the deſcendents by right line, require Law, but remaine ſubiect that the effects of hatred and malice which doe daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are more powerfull then the authority of the adjudged matter, and that the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſumption doth ouercome the truth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15056:38"/>againſt the which the Law can hardly finde entrance. We doe ordaine and command, that in the quarter or quarters in the which there ſhall be thee poſitiue Acts of clearnes and Nobleneſſe (euery one in the Act where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee ſhall require) ſhall holde for being paſſed in an adjudged matter and ſhall bee executed, and by vertue thereof to require a Royall due for the deſcendents by a right line, for to remaine qualified by Nobles and pureneſſe, for all the Acts which ſhall be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſaid party, and ſufficiently to proue the deſcendence of the perſons which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the ſaid three Acts, as it is treated in the <hi>Hidalguias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it is to be vnderſtood, that although the ſaid three Acts haue beene gained in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Courts, Tribunals, Communalties, or Colledges, or in one onely, and in reſpect of a quarter, or of two, or of all, as the Acts ſhall comprehend them. But if the three ſhall not bee accompliſhed, and ſhall haue onely one or two, Wee declare, That the ſame ſhall not bee giuen as paſſed in an adjudged matter, nor the deſcendents ſhall not require any right, and are to make new
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15056:39"/>proofes of that quality in the ordinary forme, and comming to three, it ſhall cauſe the ſaid Royall due, and comprehend it.</p>
               <p>AND becauſe the three Acts doe worke preſumption of truth, it ſhall thereby bee executed for the deſcendents, it is iuſt that they be of graue Tribunals, and whole ones, where with due knowledge of the cauſe the matter ſhall bee treated and determined of; We doe ordaine and command, that the ſaid three Acts for to worke the effect here before mentioned, are to bee of the Inquiſition, wherein there ſhall be familiatures, &amp; of the Councell of the orders, and of the Religion of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn,</hi> or of the holy Church of Toledo, or of the foure great Colledges of Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, and of the two greateſt of Alcala and Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladolid, and of no other Tribunall, Church, Colledge, or any Communalty.</p>
               <p>ANd becauſe according to law, ſometimes they returne vpon an adiudged matter, or by new inſtruments, or becauſe it hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared that thoſe which haue beene preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted were falſe, and for other cauſes enacted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15056:39"/>by Law alwayes in this matter; We doe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and command, that the three Acts in forme aforeſaid, in ſuch manner ſhall make an adiudged matter, and occaſion right to the deſcendents, that although after the ſame there ſhall be diſcouered any thing or reaſon which might be hinderfull, if the ſame had beene knowne before by any of them, the authority and effect of the adiudged matter ſhall be conſerued and remaine in his force and vigor, for it is more credit for the ſaid nobleneſſe and cleanneſſe to ſuſtaine three califications wherewith it is approued, then to diſcouer (although it is by accident to whoſe knowledge it came) who gaue it; and perſons haue enioyed the ſame, to whom it appertained not.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, becauſe many perſons with malice &amp; naturall curioſity, more then for conueniency or other good effect, do keep in their power, bookes which they call <hi>Verdes,</hi> or of leather, and Regiſters, and Catalogues of deſcendents fabricated without more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority nor cauſe, then that which his owne indignation hath offered; wherby there hath and do ariſe vnreparable &amp; iniuſt damages,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15056:40"/>as well of the nobleneſſe, as of the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and publique quietneſſe, becauſe there was onely ſeene written in theſe bookes and Regiſters certaine Families, they qualifie them for noted; and the depoſition of one witneſſe who hath ſeene the ſame, or hath heard ſay that the ſame were, it is not enough for defence, being ordinarily the moſt ſureſt, that they haue no ſubſtance, nor know not the cauſe and ground of their beginning.</p>
               <p>Wee doe ordayne and command, that no perſon of what eſtate, quality, and condition ſoeuer hee bee, ſhall not, nor may not keepe any booke in his power, Regiſter, nor Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, nor other paper, wherein it is treated of the clearneſſe of Families, or deſcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and that he burne thoſe which hee hath, vpon penalty of fiue hundred Duccats, to be applyed in three parts, for the Chamber, Iudge and Denunciator, and two yeares ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment from the place where hee is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant, and from this Court fiue leagues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> becauſe in ſome Councels and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunals, particularly in that of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the firſt inſtitution, it is vnderſtood,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15056:40"/>that ſome perſons which were called before them, examined be themſelues, and of their quality, confeſſed ſome things which were not true, nor had cauſe nor reaſon for it, and ſuch like Confeſſions haue prejudiced their Deſcendents, being ſo, that according to Law, if it ſhould bee proued the contrary of that which they containe, they cannot prejudice, becauſe the truth doth not moue for the only will: Wee ordaine and command, that if the ſaid Confeſſions be not helped with ſome other reaſon whereby it may be induced, that the matter is not in ſole termes of confeſſion, it is not ſufficient to hinder the nobility and pureneſſe, but proceed to qualifie it, as if the ſame had not beene, and according to that which ſhall ariſe let the determination bee, ruling this according to law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITem,</hi> Becauſe ſome of the Tribunals and Communalties which require Acts of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and cleanneſſe, doe draw nearer or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter more then other qualities of the proofe and qualification, and particularly the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, not contenting themſelues with the affirmatiue how that they are cleane, but alſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15056:41"/>require, that the contrary hath not bin heard nor doubted, which quality and verification hath giuen occaſion that many families re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine noted vniuſtly by the malice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred wherewith many goe forwards in this matter, and if now it goe in the ſame forme beſides the foreſaid inconueniences, it would preiudice the reſt of the Communalties and Tribunals, in the which they require nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; pureneſſe; We do ordaine &amp; command, that all that which is diſpoſed and contained in this Act, be kept, accompliſhed, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vniformally and equally in all Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, Communalties and Colledges, without any exception or difference.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:15056:41"/>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XXI.</hi> Meanes for increaſe of people.</head>
               <p>LIkewiſe becauſe the increaſe and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people, is the onely and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall foundation of Common-wealthes; for the increaſe and conſeruation whereof, greater diligence and care is to bee applyed, though that many thinges contained in this Act, doe in ſome ſort prouide, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto directed; deſiring to hinder and ſtay the Diminution herein, which dayly encreaſeth, and to preuent the cauſes from whence it hath proceeded, and to diſpoſe the matters of Gouernment, and quiet of the Subiects, in ſuch ſort that there may be hoped great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication and increaſe; and conſidering the great importance that there is, to procure by all wayes and meanes, that this our Intention may haue his deſired effect, hauing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the greateſt meanes which may bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleable hereunto: Wee doe ordaine and Commaund, that no perſon of what eſtate, condition, or quality ſoeuer, may depart out of theſe our Kingdomes with his Houſe and Family, without our Licence, vnder penalty of the loſſe and forfeyture of the goods that they ſhall leaue therein, and that the Iuſtices,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15056:42"/>and Officers of the Ports, and any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoeuer, may ſtay and detaine the ſaid perſons and goods, that they ſhall carry with them, and ſhall be very carefull to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the departure of any, and diligent for the execution; and whoſoeuer ſhall not obſerue the Contents of this Act, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of his Office.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe becauſe by the great concourſe of people in this our Court, and the great multitudes which reſide in the Citties of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi> and <hi>Granada,</hi> there ariſe many inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, as well by the number which liue Idely, and the danger wherein they liue, in ſuch a confuſion, &amp; the meanes wherby they procure their maintenance, as in the other Cities, Townes &amp; Villages of the Kingdome, for the great importance, that there bee an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in all partes, that the Land may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and Iuſtice better adminiſtred, Wee doe Commaund, that as touching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of this our Court, that therein there may not bee more perſons then need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo great a concourſe be diminiſhed, and euery one may be knowne, who hee is, what Occupation, or cauſe of reſidence hee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15056:42"/>pretendeth, and how long hee hath reſided, that the confuſion hitherto may bee remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; being preciſely obſerued and kept, that which is ordayned concerning the Regiſters and Diuiſions, and ſhall bee ordayned by thoſe of our Counſell; and for many reaſons of vniuerſall benefit which haue beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. Wee doe likewiſe Commaund, that thoſe ſixe Diuiſions, whereinto the Court is diuided, and in euery one of which, one of the Iuſtices of our Houſe, and Court, with his Officers is commaunded to liue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, bee deuided into ſixteene Diuiſions, the moſt proportionable that may bee, and that in euery one of them, doe reſide ſome one of our Counſell, in the Houſes which Wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund to bee allowed for them, who wee Commaund and Charge carefully to know and vnderſtand, the quality of the people that liue therein, and the Profeſſions and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they haue, what occaſions there are of ſcandales and offences towards God, and whatſoeuer elſe ſhall bee executed and done in the ſaid Diuiſion, that by the Authority of his perſon and Office, hee may procure it to reſt in a conuenient and ſetled eſtate, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15056:43"/>that for the accompliſhing and executing of the diligences and occaſions which ſhall bee offered, there bee appointed to euery one a Purſeuant of the Court, which ſhall liue in the ſame Diuiſion, and that the Iuſtice of the principall Diuiſion, ought to repaire to thoſe of our Counſell, who ſhall liue within it, and giue an account to them of what ſhall happen, and that they may appoint him what ſhall ſeeme conuenient, that by this care and correſpondency there may be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and accompt of the whole.</p>
               <p>And wee Commaund, that hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, no perſon of what eſtate, condition, or quality ſoeuer, may come to liue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide with his Houſe and Family in this our Court, or in the ſaid Citties of <hi>Siuill,</hi> and <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada,</hi> nor may bee admitted or ſuffered in them, vnder puniſhment of a Thouſand Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of the perſon offending, and from the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice &amp; Gouernment, who ſhal admit &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to liue there, from each particularly Two hundred Duckets, and let it bee ſet downe for an Act to remaine.</p>
               <p>And becauſe by the non-reſidence of the Nobility and Gentry at their houſes and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15056:43"/>there haue beene found moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous inconueniences, as well in the publicke gouernment of the Kingdome, and whereby the neigh bourhood &amp; Villages are decreaſed and depopulated; for that it is moſt abſolute, that the ſeruants and vaſſals which were ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained by them, doe follow them, and in the part where they goe, doe liue idlely and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accommodated, &amp; for that thoſe that remaine behinde, and are not wel gouerned, nor main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in peace and Iuſtice, as they ought: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the Iuſtices carefull to remedy it, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in many caſes and occaſions proceed ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, ſeeing themſelues ſuperiours, from whence reſulteth the morgaging and decay of their houſes and eſtates: ſeeing beſides the loſſe of the commodity, and ſmall charge, wherewith euery one liueth vpon his owne, and the Obligations in the Court, and other great places, being greater; the expences muſt needes be greater, and therefore they encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and the Tenants and Rents decreaſing, (becauſe all ſuffer declination, and decay by their abſence) it is of abſolute neceſſity, that they muſt conſume and decay: and although their owne conueniencie, being ſo well
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15056:44"/>knowne, might be ſufficient to oblige them to procure the remedy, that there might be no defect of our part, that it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. We ordaine, and commaund, that all the Lords, Knights, and other perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, who ſhall haue their eſtates, rents, and goods, charged with Fines and amercements, belonging vnto vs, with condition to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme them within a certaine time, may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the ſaid time, within the which they ought to make the ſaid redemption; with condition that this be, and is vnderſtood to be, being reſident in ſome place of his eſtate, or where they ſhall be neere, and ſo we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke that which is contained in the ninth Act, the third title of the fourth Booke of the compilation, by the which our Officers may make their demaund in this our Court, and we commaund to make them in thoſe parts, where conformable to right they ought, that by occaſion of ſutes, they may not leaue their eſtates, nor continue their reſidence in this Court.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, we permit that the Strangers of theſe Kingdomes (ſo that they be Catholikes, and friends of our Crowne) who will come
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15056:44"/>to exerciſe their profeſſions and labours, may haue free liberty: and we commaund, that actually exerciſing any Trade or labour, and liuing twenty leagues within the land from the Ports, they be for euer free from the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute money, and for the ſpace of ſixe yeares from Subſidies, and ordinarie and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſeruices, and likewiſe from the common and publike charge, in the place where they ſhall liue, and that they be admitted, as the reſt of the neighbours, to all commodities; and we doe charge the Iuſtices, to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date them with houſes and lands, if they ſhall haue neede. And other Strangers, although they be not Crafteſmen nor Labourers, hauing liued in this Kingdom the ſpace of ten yeares, with a family, and being married to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of our Dominions the ſpace of ſixe yeares, bee admitted to the Offices of the Common-wealth, ſo that they bee not high Sheriffes, Gouernours, chiefe Iuſtices, Maiors, Sheriffes, keepers of pledges, Receiuers, Clerks of Aſſiſes, Receiuers of pawnes, nor others of gouernment: for as concerning this and eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Benefices, wee referre them to our Lawes: and wee commaund the Iuſtices to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15056:45"/>accommodate them in all that may be, with houſes and lands for their labour, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, which is conſidered by their abode, with theſe conditions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cha. XXII.</hi> That there may not bee Schooles of Grammar but in Cities and Townes, where there ſhall be a Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty.</head>
               <p>IN like manner, becauſe there are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered many inconueniences, by hauing Schooles of Grammar in ſo many parts of this Kingdome, ſeeing that in ſo many places, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can bee had commodity for to teach it, nor thoſe which doe learne it, doe gaine the neceſſary fundaments for other faculties, are rather ſo ill taught, and inſtructed, that they faile altogether of the neceſſary principles and rudiments, and without ability or diſpoſition to profit in them; and ſo, many proceede vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to greater ſtudies, and looſe the time which they haue imployed in learning the Latine, which being imployed in other Myſteries and Occupations, had beene more profitable to them, and to the Common-wealth. Wee commaund, that in theſe our Kingdomes, there be no Schooles of Grammar, but in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Townes, where there bee Iuſtices, wherein likewiſe may enter Lieutenants, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, and the chiefe Iuſtices of places of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15056:45"/>the Orders, and onely one in euery Citie and Towne; and that in all the foundations of Schooles or Colledges which are; with charge to read Grammar, the Rent whereof doth not amount to three hundred Duckets, it may not be lawfull to reade: And we doe forbid the power to erect or finde any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Schoole of Grammar, with a greater or leſſe Rent then three hundred Duckets, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it ſhall bee (as aboue ſaid) in a Citie or Towne, where there ſhall be a Iuſticeſhip or Tenencie; and if it be erected, it may not be taught vnleſſe therein there be no other: for in ſuch a caſe we doe permit, that it may bee founded and erected, the Rent amounting to three hundred Duckets and no leſſe. And likewiſe wee commaund that there bee no Schooles of Grammar in the Hoſpitals, where expoſed and forſaken children are brought vp and educated, and that the Gouernours and Superintendants haue care to apply them to other Arts, and particularly to the exerciſe of the Sea, wherein they ſhall be very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by reaſon of the want there is in the Kingdomes of Pilots. But wee will that the Schooles and Seminaries bee preſerued,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15056:46"/>which ought to be according to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cha. XXIII.</hi> That the publicke Stewes bee aboliſhed.</head>
               <p>IN like manner, becauſe wickedneſſe and corruption, to the height whereon Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is aſcended, hath changed the nature and effects of excuſing greater miſchiefes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon is founded the tolleration &amp; permiſſion of the publick Stewes, in ſuch ſort, that it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeareth, that they rather adminiſter occaſion, meanes, and diſpoſition, that the ſame effects are committed, which would bee preuented, and that they ſerue onely as a profeſſion of Abhominations, ſcandales, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and the corruption of many people; and becauſe it is vnlawfull to permit this in ſo Chriſtian a Common-wealth, and that Wee are Religiouſly bound to preuent, and cut off all offences, and occaſions of offences towards God, and eſpecially of this quality, ſeeing that by the contrary ſome great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment may iuſtly bee feared, hauing thereby ſo highly prouoked and diſpleaſed his Diuine Maieſty; and particularly a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proneneſſe and diſpoſition, then that is fitting being Diſcouered, in all places and in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15056:46"/>all kinde of people; And therefore the ſaid publicke Stewes haue remained in few parts, where they are leſſe hurtfull and offenſiue, by reaſon of the number of Women, that there abound; and the diuers wayes that wickedneſſe hath inuented for the execution of this offence; And hauing conſidered, that holy Kings, and well gouerned Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealthes haue preuented this michiefe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any inconueniences that inſued, rather many conueniences thence proceeded in the ſeruice of GOD, and the Gouernment.</p>
               <p>Wee doe Ordaine and Commaund, that from hence forward, in no Citty, Towne, or Village of theſe our Kingdomes, it may bee lawfull to permit publicke Stewes, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon houſes, where Women may make a profite and ſale of the vſe of their Bodies; and Wee doe prohibite and forbid them, and Commaund them to bee aboliſhed, and ſtrictly Charge thoſe of our Counſell that they haue particular care for the execution hereof, as of a matter of great importance; and that the Iuſtices euery one in his precinct and Diuiſion doe execute the Contents here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, vnder Penaltie, that if in any part they
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15056:47"/>ſhall conſent, ſuffer and permit them, for the ſame offence, ſhall bee depriued of his Office, and condemned in Fifty thouſand Maraue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, to bee applyed in three partes, to wit, our Chamber, the Iudge, and Informer, and this Act to remaine for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>All which wee Commaund to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, executed, and kept; any Law, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or Statute made to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding: becauſe in ſo much as they are contrary hereunto, Wee doe reuoke them, and wee Commaund, that ſo yee cauſe them to bee executed and kept; in all thinges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as in our Edict is contained and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and that againſt the tenor and forme in no manner, now, or at any time hereafter yee proceed, or conſent to proceed. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may bee manifeſt and notorious, and none may pretend Ignorance, wee Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund that this our Edict bee publickly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in our Court, and that neither one, or other doe any thing to the contrary, vnder Penaltie of Our diſpleaſure, and of Thirty thouſand Marauedis to bee confiſcated to our Chamber.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Court of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> 
                  <date>the Tenth day of February. 1623.</date>
               </dateline>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:15056:47"/>
               <signed>By the King.
<hi>Approued by</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Don Franciſco de Contreras.</item>
                     <item>Iuan de Frias.</item>
                     <item>Gilimon de la Moua.</item>
                     <item>Melchor de Molina.</item>
                     <item>Don Alfonſa de Calriera.</item>
                     <item>Don Fernando Remires Iaruias.</item>
                  </list>
J <hi>Pedro de Contreras Secretarie</hi> of the Kings moſt excellent Maiestie, cauſed it to be written by his commandement.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>IN MADRID: <hi>By</hi> Tomas Iunti, <hi>Printer to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie.</hi> Anno Domini 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publication_notice">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:15056:48"/>
            <head>Publication.</head>
            <p>IN the Towne of <hi>Madrid</hi> the eleuenth day of February 1623. before the Palace and Court of his Maieſtie, and at the gate of <hi>Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalaiara,</hi> where is held the commerce and Traffique of the Merchants and Tradeſmen, in the preſence of the Licentiats <hi>Don Miguel de Cardenas, Don Luis de Paredes,</hi> and <hi>Don Diego, Francos de Garnica,</hi> Iuſtices of his Maieſties houſe and Court, was publiſhed the Act and ordinance contained in this other part, with Trumpets and Drummes, by publick Criers, with high and intelligible voyces: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto were preſent, <hi>Jnſepe de Vrraca, Franciſco de Meſa,</hi> and <hi>Franciſco Sanches de Acoſta,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables of the Kings Maieſties houſe and Court, and many others. Which was done before me</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fernando de Valeto.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15056:48"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
